Get into it, if that's okay.
Absolutely. Thank you very much, Chair.
Thank you, members, for
having us back to update you on progress in response to
the
inquiry's recommendations since we last were here in February.
My name is Alastair Herkes. I am the Interim Chief Executive
of the FMA.
There you go.
With me, I have Liam Mason, Executive Director of
Governance, Policy and Strategy, and General Counsel,
and Claire Bolingford, who is the Executive Director of Licensing and
Conduct Supervision.
So
we have provided a response to your earlier written questions,
and we're happy to
answer any questions you have.
Fantastic. I might kick off, if that's all right, and then, members, feel free to
raise your hands.
Thank you for your submission, and thank you for making the time today.
I wish we'd probably made it a little bit longer to justify your time, but
nonetheless, we are keen to continue the evolution of the banking inquiry and
what hurdles may or may not stand in the way.
You touch on the sandbox work that you're doing around on-ramping and
fintechs, and really encouraged by that.
What are you doing to, I guess, accelerate that opportunity,
understand the regulatory barriers in the market?
Because obviously that's been a success, and we'd like to see more of that.
Yeah, sure. I might take this, if I may.
The first pilot showed us some
very interesting things, one of which is that it's the base
cost of entering the regulatory sphere
is very high for small to medium firms.
Most of the firms that showed interest in the sandbox were startups,
and the feedback we heard from them is that the
fixed costs, if you like, of applying for a license, particularly when you're at
the trial stage,
are prohibitive. And that's why in the next phase we are
developing an on-ramp, what we're calling on-ramp licensing,
a streamlined licensing solution to allow smaller
firms to come into the market, into the regulatory space, so that they're
not spending their time trying to find a way to avoid it,
in a way that allows them to test their products.
Mm-hmm.
Can I just ask you a question about that?
Thank you. Hello, sorry for being late.
I'm interested in the on-ramp licenses, the e-money licenses.
It's a genuine question. I don't understand why we are still talking about them
sort of at the similar stage to what we were in '22.
Can you help us as a committee sort of understand the
points of tension in the system, I guess, to be able to introduce
that? For context, we've got fintechs in the market now that are looking at RBNZ's
announcement that they might be able to use the term bank and thinking that will
be a better
route for them. But obviously they have-
Mm-hmm
... to undertake a lot of services that are out of sequence for them, and if they
were to grow a bit more naturally and in line with other competitors, say, in
Australia, they'd be looking for your licensing.
Yeah, sure. And where we're starting with the on-ramp license is
the managed investment scheme license, which is something
that's been in place since, operational since 2016.
But it was designed at a time when it was fairly document heavy, and designed for
what I'll call mainstream managed funds.
But it's actually quite a flexible type of license.
So we've been out in the market over the last couple of months, testing what
we're calling a straw man for that.
The reason is we want to make sure that what we design actually works for the
participants,
rather than just being a sort of
regulated design solution.
Yeah.
Feedback we've got is very constructive on that,
and we'll be consulting further towards the end of
August on a more formed up plan for that.
And can I just ask this at the moment?
So as I understand it, that's more like the old
system where you've got major investors, they're over a financial cap.
They don't need the same sort of disclosure because they are majors.
So the products that you're building there are
simply cutting out the old PDS.
What is the hold-up, though, for the licenses where you've got fintechs wanting
to deliver services directly for consumers and to use
payments as part of their offering then?
So there have been a couple there,
and we did look at that through the first phase of the sandbox, which is,
we cover this in our tokenization discussion paper that we put out.
New Zealand doesn't really have a regulatory way to
recognize payments-
Yeah
... outside of banking, and what we're doing is what
we can with the financial services license,
which also wasn't designed for payments.
So we've found some solutions that have helped individual firms so
far, such as we designated the stablecoin offered by
ECDD as not a financial product, to allow that to come to market,
and we think with the flexibility of the managed investment schemes, we will be
able to help more small firms. It's not intended for the large investors
necessarily.
The exemptions that we gave in the
first part of the sandbox for some of the players were actually for very small
investments to encourage retail participation.
So we're hopeful that we can do the same with this.
Okay.
You sort of set entirely new thing. Dan?
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Thanks for coming before us today and for what your
team do. Just want to switch to another part of the banking inquiry
around transparency.
FMA, you've got this OCR pass-through
dashboard, which
I've been looking at quite a lot and seeing
fairly consistent decreases in time to pass through OCR reductions.
I'm wanting to know if you've got any learnings from how
that dashboard's working.
Has it actually resulted in, in light of transparency, has it
resulted in-
Greater reductions in passer of OCR reductions.
And then secondly, if there's any learnings for how you can bring
greater transparency to the
way fees and actions are set by banks
using the same principles of what you've done here. Thank you.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I might pick that one up, if that's okay. Thank you for the question.
So
yeah, the data set is just about a year old now,
and so it's still relatively early days in terms of the trend analysis that we're
seeing. But to your question, I think we are seeing some
interesting insights in that in terms of the timing, as you say, and that varies
between entities. So we can see that quite transparently.
This is what we call a sunlight mechanism, so it means everybody's got access to
the data, and we think that's helpful for customers and
actually for the wider community in terms of understanding what's happening.
We are also seeing that new customers of floating rate
mortgages do often receive interest rate changes
earlier than existing customers, which is something that we're quite interested in,
and we'll be exploring further in our engagement with the banks on this.
And equally, floating mortgages and on-call savings account interest
rates responses don't always move together.
Mm.
So that's another area that we will be exploring the banks in terms of what the
rationale is for that and why they have chosen to move them at different
rates. So as that data set matures, we are looking to see
whether it would be helpful to expand that further.
And actually, we're looking to create a little bit more as we get more data in,
further kind of iterations of the dashboard, so that we can make different
insights available through the dashboard.
Interesting. So supplementary. So you've got a year of data.
Are there any preliminary findings of that year of data in terms
of banks' responsiveness to OCR
changes and whether they're actually coming down, and
is there any actual
results that you've got within that one year of data, or it's still too
early?
I think we feel it's a little too early to tell at this stage,
not least because
we've had different rate changes at different times.
So in terms of a trend analysis, I think we feel we need a bit more
time.
Mm.
And as I said, we will continue to engage with the banks on this topic in terms of
the underlying reasons as to why
they make some of those changes at different points in the cycle as well.
Okay. Wonderful. Thank you.
So more to come.
Adriana Williams.
Just a brief question about that. I also am a fan of that tool.
Why did it just sort of
go on the website with zero fanfare?
We would think that... This committee's very interested in it, the minister's
interested in it.
Was this another sign that things aren't all happy at the FMA?
What are we meant to read into
something which is a massive contribution to competition,
and something that's been campaigned on for a long time by members of the
community, just kind of realizing it was there one day ?
Yeah. Thank you. So
because this is the first time that we've done something like this, we did want to
what we call soft launch it. So we weren't quite sure how it was going to land.
And also, some of the participation in it is voluntary
as well, so we wanted to make sure that we got the data-
Oh
... sets quite tight for that before we
actually made more of the information that was there.
It's really important that when we're putting things out publicly,
we make sure the data's accurate and is good quality.
And so that's why last year when we launched it, we wanted to
ensure that we had the right quality controls over that before we
publicized it more widely.
What's-
Thanks, Todd. Sorry. Let's keep moving.
Oh, yeah. My question's a slightly different one.
Obviously, in our report also, we identified the
Council of Financial Regulators as an important body.
And obviously, Dr. Brenner has presented to us just in the last few weeks
in her role as the co-chair. I suppose I'm just keen to
get
some assurance, because is that now you, Mr. Hircis, acting?
Because all I want to just understand is we don't want to lose momentum on
the work that is being taken there.
And again, it's probably not the right forum today to go into,
let's just say, the changes at the FMA and some of the uncertainty.
But I just want to, I suppose, get your reassurance that one, are you going to
be, in your acting role, you're also the acting co-chair of COFA, and
are you across the work programming, and can the FMA continue to support that work?
Well, thank you, Mr. Stevenson. Yes.
As part of my role as interim CEO, I will be
stepping into the role of being one of the co-chairs, I believe, of
COFA alongside Dr. Bremner. Yes.
And the organization as a whole is
fully supportive and up-to-date in terms of the work program.
And so I will be-
Yeah. Sure
... able to be fully participating in that and fully briefed.
The first meeting
coming up of the heads is about four weeks away.
Yeah.
And so I will be attending that fully briefed and with a colleague as well.
So we will be continuing our participation.
That's good to hear. And then just a quick supplementary.
Obviously, the other thing
Dr. Bremner touched on is obviously
trying to use the COFA to actually coordinate the
requirements on all of the people in the financial services sector.
And so from the FMA's point of view,
have you made progress on coordinating
what you're going to be requiring of people and making sure, seeing how that fits
in, and yeah. What kind of visibility have you got of that now?
I might ask Liam to give a specific-
Yeah
... couple of examples.
We mentioned a couple of those when we last appeared before you.
Mm.
But working with the Reserve Bank team to coordinate our frontline
supervision, which Claire obviously leads,
and the information request there.
One example was the recent work on insurance
affordability.
Yeah.
Used that COFA connection to make sure that we had streamlined information requests
to make that as manageable as possible for the firms.
So yes, that's
ongoing work for us.
Thank you.
I'll combine two questions into one, if I could.
In terms of fintech innovation,
you've got blockchain tokenization that I know you've done your paper on.
Blockchain obviously knocking on your door, they're knocking at everyone's door.
Yeah.
Are we at the risk of falling behind Australia and Singapore in terms
of regulation? Is one of my questions, and I know that you guys are sort of
pioneering in some of that space. But I'd also like to know,
do you need legislative political
leadership or direction in terms of legislation, or have you got a sufficient
remit within your purview as FMA and the Reserve Bank
to enable and catalyze some of that ecosystem?
Sure. Thank you.
One of the themes that came through very strongly in the submissions on our
tokenization paper
was the lack of a coherent cross-government
regulatory regime in New Zealand for digital assets,
for
tokens, and for blockchain.
We believe that we can continue to make progress using the powers that we've
got.
But one of the
things that we said in our response to submissions is that we will continue
to work with government, looking for a cross-government response, yes.
Is it
just bubbling away on the never, never, or have you got milestones where
there's going to be regulatory certainty because that's what the market's really
seeking?
The certainty is absolutely what the participants want, and we can provide that
within our space.
But I think that there is some exploratory work
that COFA's looking at,
and
that I think will help us to get a roadmap that we need for the
cross-government solution, because we don't have it at this point.
I guess I'm about to go to Aruna to finish up, but I guess
the risk is that, yeah, we're doing some work, FMA is doing some work, COFA's doing
some work, Reserve Bank's doing some work, MBIE's doing some work.
Meanwhile, Singapore's moving miles ahead, Australia's moving miles ahead-
Yeah
... and billions of dollars of
bypassing New Zealand's market. So I guess, what do you
need, or what do you need to do to sort of lock some of this in?
One of the things that we think we do need is to
bring together the different parts of government for that,
and some of the work that we're doing at the moment is thinking about what will
need to be in briefings for incoming ministers after the election.
Because certainly what we're hearing from the fintech industry is there is a
very real risk of us falling behind. Yes.
So I guess, go back to my first question, does it need political leadership to help
you in that? Does the twain need to meet?
That's what he's saying.
I think it is going to need government leadership, yes.
Okay, thank you. Aruna.
Your junk insurance report was great. Thank you for that work.
I cannot think of a clearer breach of COFI than 2% loss ratio
on these insurance products. Why aren't you prosecuting?
So the report that we've done is
to effectively show insights from the industry.
So we have done, as you'll have seen from that, a lot of monitoring
activity over the course of the last year.
Yeah.
We did see some-
We should know
... we did see some good practices from the industry.
We-
And we are following up in those areas where we see poor practices as well.
That's the one thing. Okay.
The end.
Thank you for coming in. Appreciate it.
Thank you, members.
It was short-
Thank you
... but appreciate those insights.
And thank you for the work you're doing and all the best with the
work ahead of you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you, members.
Trust